<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-25T15:48:50-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sbdm/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Adventures in SBDM</title><subtitle>My experiences as an Site-Based Decision-Making Council Parent Representative for Lincoln Performing Arts Elementary School in Louisville, Kentucky.</subtitle><author><name>Ben Wilson</name><email></email></author><entry><title type="html">JCPS Reopening: On the Eve of the Vote, I Still Can’t Support It</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-on-the-eve-of-the-vote/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JCPS Reopening: On the Eve of the Vote, I Still Can’t Support It" /><published>2021-02-25T12:25:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-25T12:25:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-on-the-eve-of-the-vote</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-on-the-eve-of-the-vote/">&lt;p&gt;After blistering few weeks of back and forth between teachers, families, unions, the Board and JCPS, the JCPS Board of Education is meeting tonight to vote on JCPS Superintendent Dr. Marty Pollio’s recommendation to reopen schools. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jefferson.kyschools.us/calendar/event/special-meeting-board-education-20&quot;&gt;Click here for details and a link to watch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be watching tonight. One of the best ways to follow along in detail is with my &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/i/lists/1354430425242988549?s=20&quot;&gt;JCPS School Board &amp;amp; Media Twitter List&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before I do, I wanted to make note of the last few weeks of developments, and put down on paper how my thoughts have changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what has happened over the last few weeks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Board and its members have ramped up quickly to get a handle around JCPS’ plan and the current science and guidelines. Researching, asking for public comment and scheduling repeated public Q&amp;amp;A and working sessions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The CDC released new guidelines, the President and Governor Beshear are pushing for schools to reopen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wdrb.com/news/education/voicing-concerns-about-reopening-classrooms-some-jcps-teachers-worried-district-could-become-superspreader/article_3c24230e-7548-11eb-afe4-ff428d653ed0.html&quot;&gt;largest teacher union in Jefferson County (JCTA) released the results of a survey of its members&lt;/a&gt;, revealing a 58% majority that do not want schools to reopen, largely because they do not feel that JCPS’ efforts are up to snuff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JCPS has hurriedly reacted to this feedback, updating its plans and &lt;a href=&quot;https://wfpl.org/jcps-will-struggle-with-social-distancing-even-with-some-staying-remote/&quot;&gt;finally publicly acknowledging parent and teacher concerns and the gaps it will not be able to fully fill&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Individual schools, meanwhile, have been detailing their custom reopening plans and communicating them to teachers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://wfpl.org/ky-house-oks-bill-requiring-schools-to-open-in-person-by-late-march/&quot;&gt;Kentucky State House of Representatives approved HB 208&lt;/a&gt; which, if approved by the General Assembly, would force JCPS to reopen March 29th regardless of the Board’s decision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wymt.com/2021/02/25/kea-shares-frustrations-with-us-dept-of-education-standardized-testing-decision/&quot;&gt;US Department of Education is requiring standardized testing to happen by end of school year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a lot to take in. The net result over the past few weeks is that the vacuum of leadership and communication has begun to be filled, and some of the concerns that teachers and families have have been met. But in my estimation it’s still risky, and it may be a massive effort for little effect. Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-jcps-still-cannot-provide-adequate-social-distancing-in-classrooms-or-on-buses&quot;&gt;1. JCPS still cannot provide adequate social distancing in classrooms or on buses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a concern from day one among teachers and families - though it was not publicly acknowledged until only recently. A realization was also made (perhaps &lt;em&gt;during a board meeting&lt;/em&gt;) that this problem will only be exacerbated as more and more families are comfortable with coming back to school. At LPAS - we currently have nearly 70% of students returning. That equates to an &lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt; of 20 students per classroom. 
It can’t be done, and it’s what the CDC is recommending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said - public health officials from both state and local agencies are pushing for reopening as “safe”. Various mitigation layers in the plan and vaccinating teachers is rightfully driving that, but the majority of families (and no children) will be NOT vaccinated soon. So while from a community perspective we might be “safe”, there is &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; individual risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that vaccine appears to be showing dramatic effect and positive information around transmissability is showing up every day. In addition, the JCTA worked with JCPS to clarify (shockingly late, I might add) rules around accomodations for teachers who are at-risk or who are also caregivers. This included reserving some 200 vaccines for the family members of teachers who are at-risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-the-burden-on-schools-is-high-and-getting-higher-the-disruption-is-likely-to-be-intense&quot;&gt;2. The burden on schools is high and getting higher. The disruption is likely to be intense.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With school administration detailing plans and communicated to teachers &lt;em&gt;as we speak&lt;/em&gt;, it’s becoming clearer that the effort it will take to reopen under this plan is immense. Non-teachers will be pressed into instructional roles, and mitigation efforts throughout the day will be shared by all in the school (administration and counselors assisting in cleanup, policing kids during entry and exit, etc). This will lead to a decline in instructional time and quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, with the split option of NTI and in-person, student/teacher assignments are very likely to be upset. The NTI teacher your students have had throughout the year will likely change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have received assurances from both of the schools where I have students that everything in their power is being done (at a sprint) to comply with guidelines and lessen disruptions. But both schools have indicated that it’s going to be a huge challenge and they have concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-this-massive-effort-buys-us-little-quality-instructional-time&quot;&gt;3. This massive effort buys us little quality instructional time.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this effort will buy us - at most - 9 weeks of school at the elementary and middle level. 7 at the high school level. For elementary, that’s 45 days of in-person learning. For middle and high schools (who will be on a weekly hybrid schedule of remote and in-person learning) that’s 14 to 18 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Reopening dates depend on grade level. Here&amp;#39;s the proposed line-up:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;— K-2nd return March 17&lt;br /&gt;— 3rd-5th return March 18&lt;br /&gt;— Early childhood return March 22&lt;br /&gt;— Middle and high return April 5&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Olivia Krauth (@oliviakrauth) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/oliviakrauth/status/1365001096318517248?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 25, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus - the Department of Education recently announced it is requiring standardized testing - so a considerable amount of precious instructional time will be given over to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The counterpoint here is that mental health and community / economic impact from schools not being open is real. But at what risk and cost to schools and teachers are we willing to take on to achieve a &lt;em&gt;short term&lt;/em&gt; impact? It feels very high to me - and we have not heard a peep about critical summer programs or the fall semester yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally - if student achievement or the wellbeing of the most in-need students was really what was driving this - why did we not get &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; into schools (safely) first?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I wonder why our reopening plans don&amp;#39;t include a way to identify those students, reach out to those families and get them back into the buildings first? This way we can (1) get kids caught up who have fallen behind, (2) practice/perfect the districts COVID protocols,&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Corrie Shull (@corrieshull) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/corrieshull/status/1364725900361797634?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 24, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still feel that to attempt a half-measure right now is just not worth it, and worse, it’s still unsafe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep thinking about this as JCPS attempting to land an airplane on the last 10 feet of runway, where the runway is the rapidly closing 2020-2021 school year. You could do it, but at what effort and what risk? Just go around, plan a better landing for the fall semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; confidence that the administration, teachers and staff at my two schools (LPAS Elementary and Noe Middle) are going to do everything in their power to safely and effectively get kids back learning in school. But they are unfairly bearing the brunt and the burden because JCPS didn’t. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.courier-journal.com/story/opinion/columnists/gerth/2021/02/24/amid-covid-jcps-leaders-need-better-plan-get-kids-back-class/4572516001/&quot;&gt;Joe Gerth’s Op-Ed piece in the CJ “Don’t blame teachers. JCPS brass is responsible for getting kids in school safely”&lt;/a&gt; says all this better than I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I was on the Board, I would vote no and would immediately start pressing for immediate focus on those most in-need and at-risk as well as planning for 100% in-person summer programs and the fall semester.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Wilson</name></author><category term="updates" /><category term="reopening" /><category term="covid" /><summary type="html">A massive effort, considerable disruption, unknown risk all for little gain.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JCPS Reopening: A Lot of Communication Issues Coming to a Head, No Vote In Sight Yet</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-a-lot-of-communication-issues-coming-to-a-head/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JCPS Reopening: A Lot of Communication Issues Coming to a Head, No Vote In Sight Yet" /><published>2021-02-22T23:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-22T23:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-a-lot-of-communication-issues-coming-to-a-head</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-a-lot-of-communication-issues-coming-to-a-head/">&lt;p&gt;It’s February 23rd, and we are still awaiting a recommendation from Superintendent Dr. Pollio on reopening JCPS to in-person schooling. What seemed like an inevitability only a couple of weeks ago now appears to have been stopped in its tracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might assume that with new CDC guidelines, the weight of the Presidency and vaccines behind reopening, this would be a slam-dunk, right? No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should have been, except that JCPS has failed until just recently to substantively listen to it’s two main bodies: the teachers and the families of students. It’s possible they have been listening and just not said anything - but that doesn’t explain the sudden about-face on a vote on reopening. What does explain it is the tide of feedback from teachers and families (in addition to the newly released CDC guidance) swamping JCPS’ rushed attempt to reopen schools in person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now, there is not currently a date set for reopening or a vote by the board to reopen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do, however, have another &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCJCC8xo7s9vxfFZiV5ZoocQ&quot;&gt;JCPS Board “Working Session” with medical experts to discuss CDC Guidelines tomorrow, February 23rd at 6PM on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;INBOX: The Jefferson County Board of Ed is meeting tomorrow night to discuss the reopening plan and the newest CDC guidelines with a group of medical professionals.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There will NOT be a vote tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jess Clark (@jess_m_clark) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jess_m_clark/status/1363967240236843012?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 22, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jefferson County Teacher’s Associaton (JCTA) survey that was delivered Friday, February 12th, days before Dr. Pollio’s anticipated recommendation to reopen schools. After weeks of near-zero communication between JCPS and teachers, JCPS got an earful. 58% of teacheers said “no” to returning. There were “400 pages” of comment attached, according to the CJ’s Olivia Krauth. These concerns ran the gambit from student safety to the safety of teachers’ families at home, to employment and school function concerns. (Read more coverage of the JCTA survey from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wdrb.com/news/education/voicing-concerns-about-reopening-classrooms-some-jcps-teachers-worried-district-could-become-superspreader/article_3c24230e-7548-11eb-afe4-ff428d653ed0.html&quot;&gt;WDRB&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.courier-journal.com/story/news/education/2021/02/18/kentucky-teachers-got-vaccine-why-some-schools-arent-reopened-yet/6763680002/&quot;&gt;the CJ&lt;/a&gt;) By the following Monday, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wdrb.com/in-depth/jcps-teachers-union-strike-deal-on-classroom-reopening-strategy/article_18ea7332-6fc8-11eb-8924-37b38f763427.html&quot;&gt;JCPS and JCTA had struck a deal on reopening&lt;/a&gt;. The recommendation was put off indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the next &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8EYqUDT61kI&quot;&gt;JCPS Board Meeting on Tuesday February 16th&lt;/a&gt;, Dr. Pollio characterized the responses from teachers  as “a lot of communication issues”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During that same Board Meeting, the JCPS Board levied some of it’s most direct and focused questions to Dr. Pollio and the JCPS administration in attendance. It was welcome and representative of their increased focus and dedication to this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since late January, the Jefferson County School Board has been responding to increasing intense public pressure. Scrolling back through &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/i/lists/1354430425242988549?s=20&quot;&gt;the increasingly active Twitter feeds of board members&lt;/a&gt;, and in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCJCC8xo7s9vxfFZiV5ZoocQ&quot;&gt;watching the (now weekly) board meetings on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;, you can see the Board finally get on top of a conflict they did not really want to or were prepared to have to adjudicate. Their increasingly critical, increasingly focused questioning - fueled by the concerns of teachers and families - have made it clear to JCPS that the Board isn’t ready to support reopening until concerns are met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So - where does that leave us now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you remember, way back two weeks ago, Dr. Pollio said that we could be ready to reopen as early as mid-March. That appears unlikely now as tomorrow the JCPS Board of Education is hosting another “Working Session” with medical experts to discuss the CDC Guidelines with NO VOTE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears that some of the teacher’s concerns were met in the deal struck, and JCPS is increasing its detailed communication to teachers and parents (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3xszvv3PzVg&quot;&gt;watch the February 18 Town Hall Meeting that featured questions from JCPS families&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are some concerns - like social distancing - that are unlikely for JCPS to overcome for those concerned. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8EYqUDT61kI&amp;amp;t=4565s&quot;&gt;See this exchange between Dr. Corrie Shull and Dr. Pollio from the 2/16 meeting&lt;/a&gt;). It will take some change in JCPS accomodations, some change in the pandemic for this to be overcome. The former is unlikely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wdrb.com/in-depth/some-jcps-employees-struggling-to-schedule-covid-19-vaccine-booster-shots/article_9390128c-7558-11eb-b2cc-53520bdcd3eb.html&quot;&gt;some JCPS teachers are struggling to scheddule vaccine booster shots&lt;/a&gt;, and detailed individual reopening plans have not been finalized by schools or communicated to teachers. I know these plans, which include details like “which teacher will my student be assigned” are being actively, hurriedly worked on in the two schools where I have students. I’m sure teachers will have plenty of questions - as will families when they are eventually communicated by the schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which leaves us here - only 3 months to the end of the regular school year. Charitably, we could get elementary and middle schools back in late March, leaving two months, less Spring Break. Middle and high schools would operate on a hybrid schedule of remote and in-person school, meaning even fewer “in person” days for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the US Department of Education wants schools to complete standardized testing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;This could mean Kentucky&amp;#39;s largest district will spend a significant portion of its few potential in-person instruction days proctoring standardized tests. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/bF7r2F0tAA&quot;&gt;https://t.co/bF7r2F0tAA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Olivia Krauth (@oliviakrauth) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/oliviakrauth/status/1364000176650747904?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 22, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My two students won’t be returning to school in-person this year largely because I don’t believe that JCPS can effectively mitigate the spread of COVID through social distancing, but also because I don’t believe that (&lt;a href=&quot;https://benwilson.org/sbdm/statements/statement-against-reopening-jcps-for-in-person-school/&quot;&gt;and haven’t believed&lt;/a&gt;) that reopening for this short amount of time is worth the massive effort and disruption required. Let’s get people vaccinated and then reopen with quality in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other required reading:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wfpl.org/jcps-reopening-plan-what-you-need-to-know/&quot;&gt;WFPL: JCPS’ Reopening Plan: What You Need To Know&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/i/lists/1354430425242988549?s=20&quot;&gt;My Twitter List of JCPS Board Members &amp;amp; Journalist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Wilson</name></author><category term="updates" /><category term="reopening" /><category term="covid" /><summary type="html">A quick update on the twists and turns in the JCPS reopening debate.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SBDM Meeting Notes: February 16, 2021</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/meetingnotes/feb-16-2021-notes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SBDM Meeting Notes: February 16, 2021" /><published>2021-02-16T19:58:53-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-16T19:58:53-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sbdm/meetingnotes/feb-16-2021-notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/meetingnotes/feb-16-2021-notes/">&lt;p&gt;Hello LPAS Families and Friends! Below are my notes from the February 16th 2021 LPAS SBDM meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: I’m one of two parent reprensentatives, so my notes are slanted towards parent/family topics. As far as notes go, they are probably incomplete, and are definitely not “official”. Official agendas and approved minutes are posted on the&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://lincoln.jefferson.kyschools.us/groups/14915/site_based_decision_making_council_sbdm/sbdm&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LPAS SBDM page&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://sppublic.jefferson.kyschools.us/sbdm/SitePages/Home.aspx&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;JCPS SBDM Council and Standing Committee Minutes site&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;good-news&quot;&gt;Good News&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Playground equipment is now complete. Thank you PTA!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shoutout to Ms. Jones for her Minecraft Clubs!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also: Student Spotlight is a hit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://lincoln.jefferson.kyschools.us/groups/14915/site_based_decision_making_council_sbdm/sbdm&quot;&gt;LPAS SBDM page&lt;/a&gt; has been updated with all dates and easy links to Agendas and Minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;committee-reports&quot;&gt;Committee Reports&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much on comittee reports - admins have been asked to focus on back to school planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CSIP Survey&lt;/strong&gt; may move to the fall. If done in spring it will be abbreviated. Ms. Case hopes it happens in the fall during “back to school” so it won’t be affected by NTI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Backpack of Success&lt;/strong&gt;. If you are interested in reviewing Backpacks, you can do so! (I’m waiting to get a link for this)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Racial Equity&lt;/strong&gt; is continuing with staff discussions of “So You Want to Talk About Race”. “A lot of good questions and conversations happening” and that she is seeing a lot of teachers relating it to real-world classroom situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;staffing&quot;&gt;Staffing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome Frank Goodlow - our new attendance clerk!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first grade teaching position has been open since the beginning of the year. Since it was beyond the “transfer period” they are currently in the lookback process, school must interview 8 people, including the person currently in the position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, one of our  4th/5th split teachers has resigned last week, and Ms. Case has reached out to all families of students affected. Hiring freeze coming up in March. There will be a sub remainder of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: See below for an update for ESL teaching related to budget.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;student-achievement-updates&quot;&gt;Student Achievement Updates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;732 books read last week “They are reading!!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;budget&quot;&gt;Budget&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a lot of movement since school isn’t spending money. LPAS spent money on school supplies (non-COVID-related) earlier in the year. They are working on having “individual schools supplies” for a return to school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Budget due March 15th, one day prior to our regular March meeting. So the week of 8th we will hold an early special meeting. Ms. Case will provide a “narrative” on the budget so that Council members do not need to parse line-by-line each budget item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to LPAS’ relatively low ESL (English as a Second Language) student-teacher ratio (“roughly half compared to the rest of the district” per Mr. Evans), and the way that LPAS is lottery-assigned students, we will be losing one of the three ESL staff we currently have. In short - under prior non-lottery student assignement plans, LPAS and JCPS had more control over the number of ESL students who were admitted. With a random lottery, the demographics are a random sampling of applicants, so staffing related to those demographics will also change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;policy-review&quot;&gt;Policy Review&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we recently completed a principal selection, our &lt;strong&gt;Principal Selection Policy was reviewed&lt;/strong&gt;. Most Council members agreed that the policy and the process was not in need of major change, as the process went smoothly. However, we did receive some pointed feedback from the school community regarding the makeup of the Interview Committee (which is the Council itself, excluding the existing principal, plus “three additional members” chosen by Council). Our policy states that the Council “will ensure a diverse representation.” The Council felt that we did this well during our last process, choosing a Committee that was diverse in race, gender, administration vs teacher, arts vs traditional. However, we agreed that as a magnet, this can be tough requirement to fill. Should we expand this to more than three? Should we require “arts” and “administration” (e.g. a counselor)? We are getting feedback from the district in regards to that. We’ll have feedback on that ahead of the second reading next month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JCPS has also asked us to &lt;strong&gt;consider adding “Policy Waivers” to our Bylaws&lt;/strong&gt;. This would allow “in extenuating circumstances” a Council to waive Council policies for a period of time. The practical guidance from JCPS has pretty light here - but we were made to understand this was allow Councils to respond to COVID-like events. As an example: suspending the “Dress Code Policy” due to everyone being remote. The example language stated that “by majority vote” a Council could waive a policy for an amount of time, and they could do so within the span of a single meeting, instead of the two meetings required by SBDM rules. I felt like this was a dramatic power to hand to a Council (or the majority of a Council), so we should definitely put limits to it. So, I suggested a couple of things: 1) that it be larger than a majority 2) there be limits to the length of a waiver. Mr. Evans suggested that instead of those things that waivers would need to be reviewed and extended month to month. That seems simple and fair, and we are set to do another reading of this next month (possibly after we seek guidance from our JCPS SBDM liasion)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;old-business&quot;&gt;Old Business&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the Principal Selection documents (council statement, survey results, etc) have been linked in the December 15, 2020 meeting minutes which you can now find through the &lt;strong&gt;new&lt;/strong&gt; SBDM Minutes link on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/155o-OecxAQ_K7wRhO5uX-FqTmXhzyYS1&quot;&gt;LPAS SBDM Page&lt;/a&gt; - officially closing out that process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, Ms. Case mentioned that she will be changing up the SBDM Policies link “over the summer” to link to individual policies. Currently it’s one big, non-searchable PDF of all the policies (though they are in alphabetical order).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-business-aka-reopening&quot;&gt;New Business AKA Reopening&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I hadn’t expected to be discussing LPAS’ reopening plans this evening (it’s not really in SBDM’s purview) - Ms. Case did state that LPAS has been working on their reopening plan, offered details and answered a number of questions from both parents and teacher representatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was very welcome - as I mentioned later to Ms. Case, the amount of official communication from LPAS or JCPS to parents has been &lt;em&gt;minimal&lt;/em&gt;, while the amount of questions, concerns and private chatter regarding reopening is &lt;em&gt;voluminous&lt;/em&gt;. Whatever she or JCPS can do to communicate with parents would be appreciated, and would go a long way to tamping down speculation and setting expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of detail, and I’m going to miss much of it, but here are my notes around the conversation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ms. Roth asked what is the current percentage of students expected to return to LPAS. Currently it is 70% in-person, 30% remote. (FYI JCPS is publishing those states in real(?) time &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.powerbi.com/view?r=eyJrIjoiM2M5YjhlYjAtMTBiYi00OTYxLWFkYTYtYWQ3YjM2MWRhNjlhIiwidCI6IjI3N2Q1NjRjLTMwYTktNGJjZS1hMThkLWFmYzhlNTQ1NDBlNSIsImMiOjN9&quot;&gt;here, for each school&lt;/a&gt; )&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;70% equates to roughly 20 students per classroom.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ms. Case offered this assessment of just how many students LPAS can safely handle by saying that “if we go from 68% to 83%” LPAS could not do that - they don’t have the space.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;LPAS’ reopening plan is due for presentation &lt;em&gt;to staff&lt;/em&gt; by the end of next week (2/26). (Note: Dr. Pollio said later that evening that ‘the third week of March’ would be the earliest elementary would reopen)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are attempting to effect all mitigation efforts possible. For example, all round “preschool” tables are being removed in favor of solo, front-facing desks (“kids facing one another is a ‘big no-no’”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ms. Craven asked about how student “Choices” (arts electives) in 4th/5th grade would affect contact tracing/cohorting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Band and Chorus &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; continue. “They can play for 30 minutes”. When I asked, Ms. Case stated that they are following &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kmea.org/home/covid-19-resources-for-music-educators/&quot;&gt;NAfME/KMEA protocols&lt;/a&gt; and she was familiar with these from her prior role at YPAS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Per Ms. Case, classrooms that have different groups of students shuttling in/out (e.g. Dance) will end 5 minutes early and staff will work to disinfect the rooms. Ms. Case stated that staff includes the teacher, the principal, counselors, whomever they have.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Teachers who “have a need” to be virtual, LPAS is going to try to make them virtual-only teachers, housing them solo in the building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms. Case did not offer her opinion on reopening, but did note that the high percentage of students returning to in-person school at LPAS does put them in very clear jeopardy of running afoul of CDC social distancing guidelines. “It’s a double-edged sword”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I share her concerns and I think the JCPS Board and teachers do as well, hence the delay of a recommendation. There are real, physical limitations to JCPS’ ability to hit the CDC guidelines. So either we reopen and fudge those guidelines or… the buildings get bigger and buses aren’t used? (On buses, Ms. Case noted that that is not the responsbility of the individual schools, but rather JCPS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those concerns and challenges aside - I feel confident that the staff at LPAS is preparing as best they can for what appears to be an imminent return to in-person school. It’s a whirlwind of shifting guidelines, science and recommendations, and it’s largely out of individual school control. But they can plan and prep, and so they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the candor and transparency in her remarks - and I hope we will hear more soon. As a reminder, JCPS is hosting a Virtual Town Hall, Thursday, February 18 at 6PM to discuss reopening. You can watch it live on &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtube.com/jcpsweb&quot;&gt;youtube.com/jcpsweb&lt;/a&gt; and they will be providing a “text line…for you to text in your questions”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you in March!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Wilson</name></author><category term="meetingnotes" /><category term="sbdm" /><summary type="html">SBDM Standing Meeting from Tuesday, February 16 2021. Principal selection policy review, staffing updates, plus reopening plan Q&amp;A</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JCPS Reopening: The New Debate of Public Health vs. Risks to Teachers and Families</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-public-health-vs-individual-risk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JCPS Reopening: The New Debate of Public Health vs. Risks to Teachers and Families" /><published>2021-02-14T18:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-14T18:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-public-health-vs-individual-risk</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-public-health-vs-individual-risk/">&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, February 16th, the Jefferson County Board of Education will meet to discuss the recommendation put forth by Superintendent Dr. Pollio. It’s expected that Dr. Pollio will recommend to reopen schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The teachers that I have spoken to are largely in the same boat as other JCPS families - attempting to take in all of the information and make an informed risk assessment, with minimal communication or acknowledgement of concerns. Frustration and confusion among those with concerns, to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Into this confusion and charged atmosphere comes the recently released CDC guidelines and the “growing body of evidence” that schools can be reopened safely - which is sure to swing public opinion further towards reopening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;https://benwilson.org/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-cdc-guidelines-nyt-survey/&quot;&gt;my post yesterday&lt;/a&gt; - this information &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; made me more confident that from a community perspective, we can safely reopen, and we should because the benefit is higher than the aggregate risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But - and this &lt;em&gt;will be the point of friction in the coming weeks&lt;/em&gt; - while the risk for the community is lower, we are transferring risks to already burdened teachers, staff and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are asking teachers and staff to take on individual risks that they have been ill-informed to assess and ill-equipped to handle. Worse, from the telling nature of the questions I have heard from teach friends (especially those with at-risk family members) they have not been granted an opportunity to have their concerns addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: only today, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cmkolb/status/1361022326746329091?s=20&quot;&gt;Board Member Chris Kolb shed light on concerns around teachers with at-risk family members or risk factors themselves&lt;/a&gt;. The CDC Guidelines suggest “temporary reassignment” for these teachers. By my accounting, JCPS’ guidelines there have been unclear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the likes of Mr. Kolb (himself not an educator by trade) there are many JCPS Board members who are educators, and they have expressed concerns similar to this. “How will social distancing be possible?” “How will it be enforced?” “What is the risk of taking COVID home to my family?” “What are the quarantine protocols?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The teachers I know are invested and involved, so I doubt seriously that this is merely teachers “not paying attention”. Given the lack of detailed communication from JCPS to families, I tend to assume this is the case for both parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect this is going to be a very contentious, fast-moving few weeks if the recommendation to reopen comes down. I honestly don’t know how the Board will vote - but from recent responses from Board members and the new guidelines - I suspect they’ll pass it with reservations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will leave JCPS steaming towards reopening (as early as March 17th), with concerned teachers and their union standing in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an unfortunately contentious position for teachers. It will likely elicit responses from the public akin to “take one for the team, like other frontline workers”. But, as a friend put it - “while teacher’s unions are in the spotlight right now, it is only because unions have been decimated in other sectors … front-line retail, grocery, restaurant, and other service industry workers haven’t forced a work stoppage on a national scale” - not because they don’t have concerns, but because they don’t have the leverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teachers, however, do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a public fight over reopening, it won’t be the teachers’ fault. They have real, legitimate concerns, and have been classically underpayed and overburdened. It’s a conversation and a negotiation that should have happened many, many months ago. Ultimately, it’s a conversation that unless addressed now, will rear its head at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you value educators, I’d suggest considering their concerns and the burdens we are (as a community) asking them to take (without a change in compensation).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Wilson</name></author><category term="updates" /><category term="reopening" /><category term="covid" /></entry><entry><title type="html">JCPS Reopening: CDC Guidelines and NYT Disease Expert Survey Bring Much Needed Leadership and Clarity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-cdc-guidelines-nyt-survey/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JCPS Reopening: CDC Guidelines and NYT Disease Expert Survey Bring Much Needed Leadership and Clarity" /><published>2021-02-13T12:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-13T12:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-cdc-guidelines-nyt-survey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-cdc-guidelines-nyt-survey/">&lt;p&gt;Things changed for me yesterday. The CDC’s “comprehensive science-based plan” for school reopening, and a New York Times survey of 175 pediatric disease specialists regarding what is important for reopening. Both strongly indicate that we can and should reopen schools, and they do so from a place of science and concensus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While my concerns about reopening from the community’s perspective is lessened with these two things - my concerns about JCPS’ ability to adhere to them and the pursuant risks still present for teachers and families are not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With clarity from leadership and science present, the work to close the gaps and address family issues is much clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NPR: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/02/12/967033554/cdc-offers-clearest-guidance-yet-for-reopening-schools&quot;&gt;CDC Offers Clearest Guidance Yet For Reopening Schools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;NYT:&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/11/upshot/schools-reopening-coronavirus-experts.html?referringSource=articleShare&quot;&gt;We Asked 175 Pediatric Disease Experts if It Was Safe Enough to Open School&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;I’ve also uploaded a &lt;a href=&quot;/sbdm/assets/We%20Asked%20175%20Pediatric%20Disease%20Experts%20if%20It%20Was%20Safe%20Enough%20to%20Open%20School%20-%20The%20New%20York%20Times.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF Version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CDC guidelines are similar to those in the past, but with notable revelations. The survey, conducted prior to the release of the guidelines, echo the guidelines. The two together provide for me two things lacking from prior conversation: science-based priorities and critical risk assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notable points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;86% of the experts polled feel that safely reopening schools &lt;strong&gt;with masking and social distancing&lt;/strong&gt; is not only possible, it’s advised.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Although these experts specialized in children’s physical health, many concluded that the risks to mental health, social skills and education outweighed the risks of the virus.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Masks and social distancing ranked clear #1 and #2 most critical efforts to be made.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vaccines for teachers (or students) are not considered critical by the guidelines or the disease experts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Community infection rate is not as high a priority as previously considered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, these clear definitions of priority and risk assessments largely settle the arguments swirling around at every level (personal, local, state, federal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: Some &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/monicagandhi9/status/1360678712010678273?s=21&quot;&gt;experts&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/katetaylornyt/status/1360325042014404611?s=21&quot;&gt;including the senior author of the Wisconsin schools study&lt;/a&gt; believes the CDCs guidelines are &lt;em&gt;too restrictive&lt;/em&gt;. Their criticisms appear to align with the results of the survey.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding JCPS - vaccination of teachers and community infection rates are two things that have been widely adopted as critcal by local officials, unions and parent groups. This is clear guidance that - at a community level - they are not as critical to “safely reopening”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-feel-confident-in-their-assessment-that-at-a-community-level-reopening-can-be-done-safely-but&quot;&gt;I feel confident in their assessment that at a community level reopening can be done safely. But…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But… neither the CDC guidelines nor this survey relieve JCPS from the challenges that their plan will continue to have with social distancing, or the concerns from individual teachers and families. I do feel that these guidelines and reports provide clearer priorities for the critical discussions and negotiations those parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the survey report highlighted: &lt;em&gt;“Just because school opening isn’t causing higher levels of community transmission doesn’t mean that there isn’t individual risk to teachers and staff”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I have been at near-zero risk for contracting or spreading the disease for nearly a year having had the privlege of working from home and doing everything I can to not catch or spread the virus. With school reopening, the risk to my family - especially if JCPS cannot mitigate the gaps in their planning - essentially triples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For teachers with families, many of whom who have been at home like me, this increase in risk is even higher, and so far without much acknowledgement (or compensation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concerns about JCPS’ ability to enforce masking (the #1 most important prevention factor) and social distancing (#2) are still here, and are very real. As the NPR article mentions: &lt;em&gt;“mask use dropped precipitously elsewhere, from just 42% on school buses and 40% in restrooms to 36% in the cafeteria”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week, JCPS Superintendent Dr. Marty Pollio is formulating his recommendation that will be provided to the JCPS Board of Education at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jefferson.kyschools.us/about/leadership/board-education&quot;&gt;the next public meeting on Tuesday, February 16th at 6PM&lt;/a&gt;. Note: They will not vote that day, but at “a later date”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there will remain concerns, the skies are finally lightening with science and leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hope is that with this information and further guidance, JCPS can mitigate the gaps in the planning and the various concerns with families and teachers to get back to in-person school. That’s the work that will get us back into school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must not forget that there are still those that are vulnerable outside the walls of the school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that, I am still hesistant to send my children back to school until my wife and I are vaccinated, and I am concerned for those teachers who are in the same spot.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Wilson</name></author><category term="updates" /><category term="reopening" /><category term="covid" /><summary type="html">New CDC Guidelines and a New York Times survey of 175 pediatrics disease specialists brings leadership and clarity to the work of reopening.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JCPS Reopening: Updates from February 9th Plan Discussion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-updates-from-feb-9th-meeting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JCPS Reopening: Updates from February 9th Plan Discussion" /><published>2021-02-10T08:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-10T08:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-updates-from-feb-9th-meeting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-updates-from-feb-9th-meeting/">&lt;p&gt;On February 9th 2021, the Jefferson County Board of Education held a special meeting - a “working session” - to present and discuss in detail JCPS’ reopening plans, and how those plans would be executed at individual schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A recommendation from Dr. Pollio is to come next week, 2/16. The Board will vote later. The earliest reopening date is currently March 17th, due to vaccine availibility.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the JCPS Superintendent Dr. Pollio and the sitting Board members, a laundry list of other JCPS officials including a selection of principals at all grade levels, were in attendance to present the JCPS plans, discuss their individual school plans, and to answer questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those following reopening and the overall &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jefferson.kyschools.us/planning-jcps-reopening&quot;&gt;JCPS plans and guidelines for reopening&lt;/a&gt; - there was little new in the reading of the plans. However, it did present an opportunity to showcase the amount of work, detail and care that individual schools are doing to comply with JCPS’ guidelines. The work is happening, and it’s a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;. It will also be a lot on the day to day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second half of the meeting was reserved for each board member, 15 minutes at a time, to question those present. Compared to the February 2nd meeting - tonight there was a notable difference in the Board’s push to have detailed answers about gaps, risks and what JCPS plans to do to mitigate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of Chairman Diane Porter’s final statements summed it up well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…the board deserves to have that information and have facts and figures before we are asked to make a vote that is serious as this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three of Louisville’s education reporters, Olivia Krauth from the CJ, Jess Clark from WFPL and Kevin Wheatley from WDRB were live-tweeting the meeting last night. It’s a great way to catch up, if you don’t have time to watch the 2 1/2 hour YouTube below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(note: click the Tweet date to see the entire Twitter thread)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Good evening — tonight&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JCPSKY?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@JCPSKY&lt;/a&gt; school board meeting is beginning. They&amp;#39;ll hear from school leaders about reopening plans but no vote is expected on a reopening date tonight. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Watch live: &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/RcQ2NaV91M&quot;&gt;https://t.co/RcQ2NaV91M&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Olivia Krauth (@oliviakrauth) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/oliviakrauth/status/1359277124981514240?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 9, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;The Jefferson County Board of Ed is meeting tonight to discuss plans for a possible return to the classroom.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is an informational session only. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JCPSSuper?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@JCPSSuper&lt;/a&gt; says the board will get more info and vote next Tuesday.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Watch here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/6dpaZ2x2gf&quot;&gt;https://t.co/6dpaZ2x2gf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jess Clark (@jess_m_clark) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jess_m_clark/status/1359278248715309061?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 9, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wfpl.org/jcps-will-struggle-with-social-distancing-even-with-some-staying-remote/&quot;&gt;JCPS Will Struggle With Social Distancing, Even With Some Staying Remote&lt;/a&gt; (February 9, 2021, Jess Clark)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Tonight&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JCPSKY?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@JCPSKY&lt;/a&gt; board work session on school-level plans for reopening is about to begin. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Follow along here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/nU9DAcb6yO&quot;&gt;https://t.co/nU9DAcb6yO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Kevin Wheatley (@KevinWheatleyKY) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KevinWheatleyKY/status/1359276003311427586?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 9, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with all &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jefferson.kyschools.us/about/leadership/board-education&quot;&gt;JCPS Board of Education meetings&lt;/a&gt; - they are streamed on YouTube, and archived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/wVKxvlzHx5A&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also did a bit of live-tweeting to capture my reactions. You can see this here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I&amp;#39;m watching the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JCPSKY?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@JCPSKY&lt;/a&gt; Board of Ed meeting on detailed reopening plans. Thoughts below in thread 1/&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ben Wilson (@mynameiswilson) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mynameiswilson/status/1359285913130532865?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 9, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/10/podcasts/the-daily/school-reopening-teachers-unions-biden.html&quot;&gt;The Daily from the New York Times today is focused on “What Will It Take To Reopen Schools?”&lt;/a&gt; - and the parallels to Louisville are again, striking. In many ways - we are actually ahead of the curve, compared to places like Chicago. So… we’ve got that going for us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Wilson</name></author><category term="updates" /><category term="reopening" /><category term="covid" /><summary type="html">The February 9th Board of Education meeting was characterized in a marked shift in questions from Board member. As Chairman Diane Porter put it: &apos;we will need specifics to make a vote of this importance&apos;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JCPS Reopening: The Wave is Coming</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-risks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JCPS Reopening: The Wave is Coming" /><published>2021-02-08T22:52:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-08T22:52:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-risks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/updates/jcps-reopening-risks/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(UPDATE 2/8: there is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jefferson.kyschools.us/calendar/event/board-education-special-meeting-5&quot;&gt;Special Board Meeting Tuesday February 9th 2021 - tomorrow&lt;/a&gt;! Public encouraged to offer comment via email)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s where I’m currently at on reopening for the remainder of this school year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still don’t support it, right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we are being told that we must reopen in-person, there continues to be a lack of evidence being offered from public health and JCPS officials that we can safely do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, I am seeing a disturbing there is a lack of acknowledgement about the risks teachers and families are being asked to accept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had to put it into a metaphor, here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There’s a big wave coming, and it’s gonna hit the beach. Most folks in power have their back turned to it. The first people it’ll hit, though, are JCPS teachers and their families.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reopening is going to happen - and frankly, needs to happen - but when and under what circumstances is the current debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attitude that I read from officials is that this choice has been made for them and that it is inevitable, and we are to move forward at all costs. Costs that even our own public health officials cannot claim to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this decision moves forward and is wrong, those directly in the path of it are teachers and their families. Yes, COVID affects the whole community, but teachers are not being given the same option of in-person or NTI teaching, effectively making the choise between their health and their jobs - a choice they did not sign up for. And worse these teachers being made scapegoats for having the same concerns we all share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of of this stems from a lack of leadership at the federal level - which if &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/video/biden-calls-covid-pandemics-impact-on-women-a-national-emergency/&quot;&gt;today’s announcement holds true will be addressed somewhat by President Biden’s approval of CDC guideliens&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But - the federal government does not make JCPS decisions. Those at the state and city level will make the decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-has-changed&quot;&gt;So What Has Changed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sbdm/statements/statement-against-reopening-jcps-for-in-person-school/&quot;&gt;Since I last wrote about it&lt;/a&gt; - nothing has changed in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jefferson.kyschools.us/planning-jcps-reopening&quot;&gt;JCPS plans and guidelines for reopening&lt;/a&gt;. There are still considerable, concerning gaps and unfair treatment of teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; changed is that the public conversation around this has grown louder. Superintendent Pollio and public health officials are responding, and the risks teachers are being asked to take are coming into sharper relief. All in all, there is mounting public pressure - especially on teachers and their unions - to return to in-person school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wave3.com/2021/02/04/mcconnell-jcps-vice-chairman-clash-over-issue-reopening-schools/&quot;&gt;Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell&lt;/a&gt; who openly chastized JCPS Board vice-chair Chris Kolb after he voiced the concerns of teachers. This is ignorant, unfair and unbecoming of a man of McConnell’s stature - but on par for his political record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I digress. A decision from the Board rapidly approaching and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wdrb.com/in-depth/jcps-teachers-support-staff-unions-polling-members-on-reopening-classrooms/article_63146ae8-67cc-11eb-bced-3340d4ebdc32.html&quot;&gt;the largest teachers union in JCPS are taking a poll of their members regarding reopening&lt;/a&gt;. So this &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be coming to a head, and soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that JCPS is on track to have all teachers vaccinated fully by early March (lord willin’ and we get the second round of vaccine doses!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-poor-argument-for-reopening&quot;&gt;A Poor Argument for Reopening&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Returning to the local and state defense of reopening - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WMJUU6hBUAo&quot;&gt;the most recent JCPS Board of Education meeting (February 2, 2021)&lt;/a&gt; featured a marathon 3-hour question-and-answer session with &lt;a href=&quot;https://louisvilleky.gov/government/health-wellness/dr-sarah-moyer-chief-health-strategist]&quot;&gt;Dr. Sara Moyer, Chief Health Strategist&lt;/a&gt; and Dr. Connie White from the Kentucky Department of Public Health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerns and tensions were high, Board members were prepared, and the answers from Drs. Moyer and White were thorough and lengthy. But I would characterize the responses on the whole as heavily favoring reopening, supported with little evidence, failing to acknowledge the known risks and without adequately addressing the detailed concerns of the Board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears as though local and state public health officials are resigned to reopening and are working to support an incredibly shaky defense while not acknowledging areas of CDC guidance that JCPS can’t achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It pains me great to hear what I heard, but it’s there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three response from that conversation stuck out to me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/WMJUU6hBUAo?t=2730&quot;&gt;exchange between Mr. Craig and Dr. Moyers&lt;/a&gt; around mental health issues that begun by floating “anecdotal evidence” of “waiting lists at psychiatric hospitals” and culminated with Dr. Moyers saying “I think [the claimed data] is what drove the state’s decision to vaccinate K-12 teachers” . She furthered this with a claim that overdoses and homicides were on the rise in children. When I reached out to Dr. Kolb, he told me this data was requested but has not been provided.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/WMJUU6hBUAo?t=5702&quot;&gt;response to Rev. Shull statement “basically we don’t know whether or not vaccinated teachers can take it home to their families”&lt;/a&gt; should have been a simple “no, we don’t”. Instead, it was a carefully worded response that equated teachers to front-line healthcare workers and “the majority of them never brought it home”. Teachers heard the risk in these words.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;WDRB reported “While she could not provide specific data, Dr. White said youth suicide attempts have increased in Kentucky recently.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wdrb.com/in-depth/city-state-health-officials-say-jcps-can-safely-reopen-as-school-board-decision-looms/article_dd0920dc-65d3-11eb-8f77-db9e5f35daa8.html&quot;&gt;WDRB, Feb 2, 2021&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, she &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/WMJUU6hBUAo?t=2380&quot;&gt;referred to UV and air filters as “voodoo”&lt;/a&gt; after a lengthy discussion around the need for airflow and then went on to &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/WMJUU6hBUAo?t=2604&quot;&gt;lean on her home improvement experiences&lt;/a&gt; to make an argument that “old buildings breath better”. Both things she admitted are not her area of expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a scientist or a public health expert but I was taught (in JCPS) that anecdotes are not evidence and correlation is not causation. If you don’t know the answer or don’t have data, you don’t claim it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the whole, I was not convinced because I didn’t think these public health officials were entirely convinced.  This leaves me feeling the argument here was weak and possibly influenced by forces outside of their control (see the wave metaphor above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of how you personally read the responses in that meeting, the summary is this: &lt;em&gt;Our local and state public health officials consider the threat to mental health as far larger than the impact of COVID, when it comes to reopening schools.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which means that they feel that less harm will come from the total effects of COVID - physical, mental, economic - if we reopen schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backing this decision is years of professional experience but woefully little data - which you can’t blame them for. COVID illnesses is easy to meausre in the short term. Mental health and other long-term effects are not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be honest and up-front about this. It’s OK. We want scientist to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;are-the-concerns-still-here&quot;&gt;Are the concerns still here?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the gaps are still here - even with the vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A growing body of US and European studies(1) - including the guidance from the CDC still say safely reopening schools rely upon things like social distancing &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;/em&gt;, airflow and a detailed approach. President Biden made it clear tonight that two of my biggest concerns with reopening - social distancing in classrooms and on buses - will be a part of the CDC guidance they are expected to push this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the response from JCPS and public health officials I heard did not even acknowledge those as requirements. It was instead a consistent refrain was that “every precaution” was being made, and that safety was “like stacks of swiss cheese”. But there are real, serious gaps, the CDC knows it and the President is likely to back it. On packed buses and crowded, stuffy classrooms with windows that won’t open and doors that the state says you can’t open. And let’s not forget that the community itself is complicit in the success or failure. We are “in the red zone”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this situation, and with these gaps, there are risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing-in--on-reopening&quot;&gt;Closing in … on Reopening&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gaps aren’t being closed. The risks are not being acknowledged. Teachers and their families - and therefore the whole community - is possibly being put at great risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend to trust Dr. Moyers and Dr. White. They have real experience and knowledge and have access to data and resources we do not. That’s a cornerstone of public trust. But when you offer no evidence and couple it with not addressing or worse - brushing aside - real, black-and-white concerns, it erodes that trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure what’s behind it exactly. These people of science appear to be brushing aside what many in the community see as real, demonstrable risk. I assume they, too, are caught up in the coming wave. Vaccines have been allotted. Teachers have been given the shot. There &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a real mental health crisis right now. There is also a real pandemic that uses our whole community as its network to spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, if the data is to be believed, I and many others think we can’t reopen safely by the measures available to us. Do we want to? Definitely. But somewhere, the risk assessment has been made that these real risks are worth reopening and possibly spreading the disease further. But the evidence for it hasn’t been shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pressure continues to mount.  This is failure from the top-down, and it’s falling on the schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m disappointed in that lack of leadership - but hopeful with President Biden’s announcement today that that will change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I still can’t support reopening from March-June 2021 until JCPS and the community take the risks more seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-forward&quot;&gt;Looking Forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after all that - I am hopeful that after we’ve vaccinated enough people to bring our infection rate down, and the gaps we have in our reopening plan have been mitigated, we will be able to safely reopen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimistically, I hope that means the fall term at the latest. I’d love for it to be this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime - wear a mask, get tested if you have to be in contact with others, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://kycovid19.ky.gov/&quot;&gt;keep an eye out when you or your loved ones are eligible for the vaccine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jefferson.kyschools.us/about/leadership/board-education&quot;&gt;next Jefferson County Board of Education meeting is slated for February 16th at 6PM&lt;/a&gt;. If you have concerns or questions, review the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jefferson.kyschools.us/planning-jcps-reopening&quot;&gt;JCPS Reopening Plans&lt;/a&gt; if you haven’t already, and contact the Board to have your voice heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emails for the current JCPS School Board are here: 
porterschoolboard@gmail.com, chris@kolbforschoolboard.com, james.craig@jefferson.kyschools.us, joseph.marshall2@jefferson.kyschools.us, lindadduncan@live.com, corrie.shull@jefferson.kyschools.us, sarah@sarah4jcps.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Louisville is not the only city struggling with reopening. In this article from the New York Times, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/08/us/schools-reopening-teachers-unions.html?referrer=masthead&quot;&gt;The Union Leader Who Says She Can Get Teachers Back in Schools&lt;/a&gt;, the parallels from Lousiville - from the strong teachers union right down to how the public opinion on reopening breaks along racial lines - are stunning. Highly worth the read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(1) Three studies indicate that safe opening requires adequate social distancing &lt;em&gt;plus&lt;/em&gt; a low infection rate in the community, among other things: &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2775875&quot;&gt;JAMA&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/sites/default/files/documents/COVID-19-in-children-and-the-role-of-school-settings-in-transmission-first-update_1.pdf&quot;&gt;EU&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/volumes/70/wr/mm7004e3.htm&quot;&gt;CDC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Wilson</name></author><category term="updates" /><category term="reopening" /><category term="covid" /><summary type="html">The decision on reopening will be on us, but real gaps and risks remain for teachers, families and the community as a whole. An update on where I stand, plus a recap of the contentious Feb 2nd Board meeting.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Statement Against Reopening JCPS for In-Person School</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/statements/statement-against-reopening-jcps-for-in-person-school/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Statement Against Reopening JCPS for In-Person School" /><published>2021-01-29T15:58:53-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-29T15:58:53-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sbdm/statements/statement-against-reopening-jcps-for-in-person-school</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/statements/statement-against-reopening-jcps-for-in-person-school/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: The statement below is the opinion I have crafted for my family. It does, however, represent the majority of the feedback I am currently capable of receiving from LPAS parents, which is limited.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late December, JCPS revealed a plans for reopening school for in-person learning, both district-wide (entitled “A New Way Forward”) and individual school plans. Read them here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jefferson.kyschools.us/planning-jcps-reopening&quot;&gt;https://www.jefferson.kyschools.us/planning-jcps-reopening&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the vaccine rolling out and the majority of teachers being vaccinated - these plans are very close to being enacted, should the School Board choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And twice now, &lt;a href=&quot;https://wfpl.org/jefferson-county-school-board-votes-to-allow-winter-sports-to-begin/&quot;&gt;the School Board has shown a deference to public pressure instead of science&lt;/a&gt; - while freely admitting they aren’t qualified to make these decisions! So please do your own due diligence, ask questions, or ask the School Board to, I don’t know - trust experts instead of public opinion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to get back to school. I want to support this plan. If the board wasn’t going to do the research, someone had to. So, I dove in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, there are some School Board members who are presenting evidence and voting no. Chief among them is District 2’s Chris Kolb, who has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kolbforschoolboard.com/research-summary-on-covid-19-sports-and-schools/&quot;&gt;published the research he’s done and presented to the board here&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a must-read, largely because it’s the only read I’m seeing from Board members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m not a medical expert, but luckily I happen to know a couple of medical doctors with first-hand experience around COVID protocols for schools and how coronavirus spreads. One created the successful in-person protocols for a local parochial school and the other an epidemiologist who studied the coronavirus (before it was “cool”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are both very concerned with re-opening &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;em&gt;this plan&lt;/em&gt;. Both of them have reviewed the JCPS plan against the recent CDC guidelines - and both say there are major gaps in JCPS’ plan and the &lt;em&gt;community itself&lt;/em&gt; don’t meet the standards of safety. In JCPS’ case - they can’t possibly. And in Lousiville’s case, they haven’t.  With their critical insights and the measured opinions of a number of friends, I’ve crafted the email and statement below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the email and the statement I sent to the JCPS School Board members today, in opposition of reopening JCPS in-person under the current timeline and JCPS plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read my full statement here: &lt;a href=&quot;/sbdm/assets/Ben%20Wilson%20-%20Statement%20on%20In-Person%20School%20Plan%20(2020.01.29).pdf&quot;&gt;Ben Wilson - Statement on In-Person School Plan 2021.01.29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Greetings -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My name is Ben Wilson. I am the parent of two JCPS students, a third grader at LPAS and a sixth grader at Noe Middle School. I am also an SBDM Parent Representative for LPAS and the LPAS current cross-country coach for 50+ students. Professionally, I am a marketing strategist, and spend much of my time interviewing and researching complex, difficult challenges. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I felt it necessarily - both personally and in a representative capacity - to do my due diligence on this subject. Speaking personally for my family, I am presenting my position to you in the attached statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is confusion in the public sphere - confusion from a lack of leadership which has fallen at your doorstep. But this - by your own admission - is not a decision you are qualified to make. As Ms. Duncan stated, regarding winter sports: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We should not be sitting here making these medical decisions.” “I think the medical community should be the one telling us what we should be doing and shouldn’t be doing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I cannot agree more. I appreciate the weight of the decision you are being asked to make - but this is not a matter to be left to public opinion or pressure. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Listen to the doctors, the scientists, the CDC. The virus is still spreading rapidly in our community. The current JCPS and individual school plans - and the wider community’s preventative measures - are not up to par.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Please vote NO on reopening in-person before these issues are mitigated. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thank you,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ben Wilson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emails for the current JCPS School Board are here: 
porterschoolboard@gmail.com, chris@kolbforschoolboard.com, james.craig@jefferson.kyschools.us, joseph.marshall2@jefferson.kyschools.us, lindadduncan@live.com, corrie.shull@jefferson.kyschools.us, sarah@sarah4jcps.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Wilson</name></author><category term="statements" /><category term="reopening" /><category term="covid" /><summary type="html">My email and statement to the JCPS School Board in opposition of the current JCPS plan and timeline for re-opening to in-person school.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meeting Notes: January 19, 2021</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/meetingnotes/jan-19-2021-notes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meeting Notes: January 19, 2021" /><published>2021-01-21T19:58:53-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T19:58:53-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sbdm/meetingnotes/jan-19-2021-notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/meetingnotes/jan-19-2021-notes/">&lt;p&gt;Hello LPAS Families and Friends! Below are my notes from the January 19th 2021 LPAS SBDM meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: I’m one of two parent reprensentatives, so my notes are slanted towards parent/family topics. As far as notes go, they are probably incomplete, and are definitely not “official”. Official agendas and approved minutes are posted on the&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://sppublic.jefferson.kyschools.us/sbdm/SitePages/Home.aspx&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;JCPS SBDM Council and Standing Committee Minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first “normal” meeting since joining the SBDM back in November! Every other meeting I’ve attended was focused Principal Selection or… the fallout from the Principal Selection. So, it was genuinely nice to be able to finally welcome to Ms. Case, speak with her directly, get down to “standard” business, and hear some great news about LPAS as we move into this next chapter of LPAS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also discussed putting a bow on Principal Selection, with two items: 1) posting the items the Council stated in December that we’d post and 2) reviewing the Principal Selection Policy in the February 2020 meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s LPAS’ turn to get vaccines! About two weeks earlier than expected!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New playground equipment coming soon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;LPAS is getting a new roof over the summer … which means no summer programs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The school’s participation rate is at 98% - well above JCPS average right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;details&quot;&gt;Details&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, a good, brisk, productive meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COVID Update! Vaccines for JCPS employees are ahead of schedule&lt;/strong&gt; and proceeding alphabetically. Lincoln staff should be up Tuesday or Wednesday at Broadbent Arena. Sooner than February 1st as previously expected. Sounds like in-person school might be a possibility? Hard to say… I heard a (non-LPAS) teacher at the donut shop last week declare (eclair?) “We won’t be going back this school year. The union is too strong” … so who knows. But things are moving ahead, plans being made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A couple of LPAS building updates:&lt;/strong&gt; New playground equipment coming soon. New roof for LPAS this summer! But… that also means no summer programs in the school. More details around that soon, I’m sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;annual Comprehensive School Survey&lt;/strong&gt; will be coming around soon - it’s open to the public and is a great way to have your voice heard. You can see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jefferson.kyschools.us/departments/data-management-research/comprehensive&quot;&gt;past results (2012-2020) here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5th Grade backpack defenses&lt;/strong&gt; coming up (April 26th-29th) - which will be during Derby Week. Not sure what Derby will look like this year, but it’ll be a busy time. Ms. Case working on quality and quantity of backpack items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Racial Equity training&lt;/strong&gt; is continuing with staff. Teachers are starting reading “So You Want to Talk about Race”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Attendance Clerk position&lt;/strong&gt; created due to Ms. Arethia’s passing closed last week. Interviews starting soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/YF-h_921ZQk&quot;&gt;Ms. Arethia was also featured on CBS This Morning in a beautiful rememberance of her life&lt;/a&gt; and impact on the LPAS community. They also call out the Arethia Tilford Sunshine Award at the end! Please watch and share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Student Achievement:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;98% participation rate (how many kids are attending NTI) - this is REAL high for JCPS, and an improvement from December (95%). The staff and counselors were credited with their direct family engagement here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100% ECE participation rate (Ms. St John! Woo!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No updates regarding KPREP yet - Ms. Roth asked if and when they go back to school, will they go into testing. Ms. Case said likely not, but they may do MAP testing to get some data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Access testing, language proficiency (ESL qualification) is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reading:&lt;/strong&gt; 309 books read last week!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Budgets are pretty static at the moment.&lt;/strong&gt; However in February we will have our proposed school budget, so get ready for that. This is an annual “big thing” for SBDM, so if you are interested - start paying attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wrapping up Principal Selection from December:&lt;/strong&gt;
Earlier this month, I had contacted the other members of the council to see where we were with the actions we said we’d take in our “Council Statement on Principal Selection”. Specifically, we said we would publish on &lt;a href=&quot;http://lincoln.jefferson.kyschools.us/groups/14915/site_based_decision_making_council_sbdm/sbdm&quot;&gt;the LPAS SBDM page&lt;/a&gt; a number of documents relative to Principal Selection - including the results of the public principal selection criteria survey. For a number of reasons - the holidays, the change in administration, etc - this had not yet been done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll save you the back-and-forth, but ultimately I suggested (and the Council agreed with a “yay”) that we would publish those documents attached to the minutes from the December 15th meeting, including a link to the video recording. (As of Jan 24th this hasn’t been updated yet. Will advise!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that effectively wrapping that process, I would like to offer a thankful coda: This change, in this moment in time, has been an emotional one. I think everyone in the LPAS Community has come to realize through this change just how invested we are in our school. You spoke out publicly, privately, to this Council, to the District and you made your voices heard. It was a little messy, but your comments and concerns informed this Council’s actions. And those actions I believe led to a realization of the needs of this uniquely invested community. Keep it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: You can read &lt;a href=&quot;/sbdm/assets/SBDM%20Council%20Statement%20on%20Principal%20Selection%20(2020.12.15).pdf&quot;&gt;the Council Statement here&lt;/a&gt;. You can also read the &lt;a href=&quot;/sbdm/assets/Reflections%20on%20LPAS%20Community%20Reaction%20to%20Principal%20Selection%202020.12.15.pdf&quot;&gt;“Reflections on LPAS Community Reaction to Principal Selection”&lt;/a&gt; statement I read during our December meeting. The Survey Results will be linked in the official December 15th SBDM Minutes on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sppublic.jefferson.kyschools.us/sbdm/SitePages/Home.aspx&quot;&gt;JCPS SBDM Council and Standing Committee Minutes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Principal Selection Policy Review: February!&lt;/strong&gt;
But wait! There’s more! (sigh)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are going to be reviewing the Principal Selection policy &lt;em&gt;next month&lt;/em&gt; at our regular meeting. If you have feedback or thoughts, please email the Council OR sign up to speak at the next meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policy reviews take two meetings - one for an initial review and reading, and the second to confirm any changes madee during the initial review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SBDM Page Updates Coming Soon&lt;/strong&gt;
The transparency and communication nerd in me was very happy to hear that Ms. Case wants to make the SBDM page much more useful - reorganizing it, ensuring that the upcoming dates and schedule are updated, contact info up to date and making the School Policies not one long, unsearchable PDF. Yay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All small things - but I’m here for anything that makes this sort of critical (but often ignored) information more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policy Reviews&lt;/strong&gt;
We had a second reading of both the Wellness policy and Discipline policies. We also reviewed the Exit from Magnet Program policy (which discusses removing a student from the school for various infractions) - and it was noted that this will likely be removed from individual school policies as JCPS will be mandating policy, similar to admissions policies. They haven’t approved yet, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaking of Writing&lt;/strong&gt;
Ms. Jones has agreed to be our permanent Secretary! Yay for Ms. Jones!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always if you have feedback, feelings, thoughts or questions regarding SBDM stuff - feel free to contact me. If you have specific questions - please contact the school!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you in February!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Wilson</name></author><category term="meetingnotes" /><category term="sbdm" /><summary type="html">SBDM Standing Meeting from Tuesday, January 19 2021. Welcome Ms. Case! Vaccines, student participation, principal selection wrap up, more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I Joined SBDM</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/aboutme/why-i-joined-sbdm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I Joined SBDM" /><published>2021-01-13T19:39:53-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-13T19:39:53-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sbdm/aboutme/why-i-joined-sbdm</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sbdm/aboutme/why-i-joined-sbdm/">&lt;p&gt;“Improving student achievement through family engagement. ALL families”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can stop reading now if you are short on time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I figure all goals should be brief like a mantra. Above is mine for anything I do for LPAS. Volunteering in class, tutoring, helping with events, working on community projects, coaching the cross-country team, or working with this SBDM Council.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s good to have a mantra - because as a representative or a leader, I’ve learned the hard way you spend a lot of time diving deep into comments, questions and concerns. It’s easy to lose sight of the big picture, the big goal. A mantra like this is a guide star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;family-engagement-for-all-families&quot;&gt;Family Engagement for All Families&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Family engagement for ALL families is my goal. Since joining the LPAS community 7 years ago, I’ve seen what it can do to raise up students and families alike like a great tide. When families connect with other families, that’s a community. Community is incredibly valuable: if you can achieve “community” so many more students thrive and succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s also precarious - most families are only there for 6 years, and there’s a constant outflow of graduation and a constant inflow of new families. To keep a dynamic community like this healthy and thriving, it requires a lot of planning and a lot of work. It also requires a dedication to principles (and princiPALs) to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my day job, I’m a  “strategist” meaning I spend a lot of time listening, researching, collaborating, planning things to get people engaged with for- and non-profit organzations. What I’ve learned is that you have to have values and principles baked into everything you do, or it &lt;em&gt;just won’t work&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-shared-concepts-that-make-engagement-work&quot;&gt;The shared concepts that make engagement work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transparency&lt;/strong&gt;: One part being open, the other part listening and responding to the needs of your community.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authenticity&lt;/strong&gt;: Walking the walk and practicing what you preach. Every. Day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Equity&lt;/strong&gt;: Making sure everyone in the community is not only seen and heard, but that they are represented.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think for the first two concepts, LPAS scores highly, but work will always be needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think for the third - equity - LPAS (and JCPS…and Louisville) could do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-i-think-the-lpas-community-needs-to-go&quot;&gt;Where I think the LPAS Community needs to go&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LPAS, like most magnet schools, is diverse by design. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://assessment.jefferson.kyschools.us/PublicDatasets/pdf/2021/47_Current_Enrollment_Race_Gender_ES.pdf&quot;&gt;See for yourself!&lt;/a&gt;) More diverse racially than Louisville itself, thanks to white flight to private schools. The makeup of the staff and the administration, their attitudes and actions have in my (admittedly white-male) perspective done a great job of making LPAS an inclusive, respectful and equitable place to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, family-involved groups (SBDM, PTA, volunteering) are not and have not been reflective of the same diversity or actions. This has been acknowledged to me personally by a number of people, but with the same wearied frustration I’m sure you’ve heard before: “We’ve tried, but…” But what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working to ensure equitable representation and opportunity is large issue - larger than LPAS or JCPS, but it’s one where schools can have an outsized impact. Schools - and specifically magnet schools - are unique places because they cross over the boundaries created by years of institutional segregation of race and economics. Elementary schoools specifically are places where many new parents come to find “their people” and forge new relationships through this shared experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s only six years, but it’s a crucial six years. And if you are committed to the community - an ever-changing, flowing, dynamic community of families present and future - then ensuring that all families are represented in your ranks and in the decisions you make is important. And I’d stake that it’s just as important as working for your child and the children of your friends for the time &lt;em&gt;they’ll be at LPAS&lt;/em&gt;. But what about those coming into the school next year and 6 years later? How will it change for them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then I ask for you to get involved and if you are involved, consider ways to help make the deeply involved community at LPAS look more like the student and family population at LPAS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get that this position is bold - but I’ve been in or around Louisville and JCPS my entire life, and frankly I’m tired of the lazy segregation we take for granted in this town. It’s robbed us all of relationships, opportunities and experiences uncountable, and I’ve been too long ignoring that fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think public schools can be a place where this change begins, and I think we are largely on the right track. But it will take work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The involved LPAS Community (volunteers, council members, etc) should look as much like it’s student and family population as possible, in all demographics: race, gender, geographics, and economic situation as possible. It doesn’t right now, and that means we’ve got work to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stood for this as the coach of our cross-country team, and I stand here now for the same as an SBDM rep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My power to affect this change directly is limited, as is the time I have on this council. So then, I want to use what I have to move us forward and engage MORE families because I know the benefit that has to students and families both. This “blog” is part of that. There will be more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-then---what-is-it-that-ill-do-to-help-this&quot;&gt;So then - what is it that I’ll do to help this?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, an SBDM Parent Representative my capability and focus is limited to the following: &lt;strong&gt;school policies&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;school budget and staffing&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;some hiring&lt;/strong&gt; (most notably principal hiring). Those things carry great weight and import - but they aren’t &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;. In-class, day-to-day and those things that JCPS has outright control over (admissions policies, for example) are things outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, there are privileges that you have granted me in electing me. A requirement of being a representative is being available, listening, and guiding. I’ll do those things and I will implore other representatives do the same. I will also push to ensure that everything the SBDM does is as &lt;strong&gt;accessible&lt;/strong&gt; as possible - meetings, notes, actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I will provide the school and the district with the insights I have as a parent and a professional strategist on ways to improve family engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, I’ll keep up with this blog as a document of my time, but also as a guide to those who come after me who are curious as to what SBDM is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve got a long way to go, but that’s the work. And I’m here for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, &lt;strong&gt;do not hesitate&lt;/strong&gt; to contact me. I want to hear from you, because that’s the job of representation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love you all! See you soon…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;🐶🐶🐶&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(You can see my candidate bio I submitted, along with all other nominees, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/u/1/d/1qPZ7u95Z_aWTji28vAffEOSWyvD_yTLFtXpQwmbwB1c/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Wilson</name></author><category term="aboutme" /><category term="sbdm" /><summary type="html">Why I ran, why I&apos;m here and what I&apos;ll do. Promoting family engagement for ALL families.</summary></entry></feed>